# **Tengxiang Zhang**

I am an Assistant Research Scientist at Pervasive Computing Research Center, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. I build pervasive interfaces to bridge the digital and physical world. My research interests include: 1) Sustainable sensing and interactive systems; 2) Thing-computer interconnection techniques; 3) Human-AI interaction and collaboration.

# **EDUCATION**

2016-2019	PhD, Human Computer Interaction, Computer Science	
	Tsinghua University, China	Advisor: Prof. Yuanchun Shi
2011-2013	MSc, Electromagnetics, Electrical Engineering	
	The University of Texas at Austin, USA	Advisor: Prof. Andrea Alu
2007-2011	BSc, Chien-Shiung Wu Honors College/Electrical Engineering	
	Southeast University, China	Prof. Tiejun Cui's Lab

# **PUBLICATIONS**

- 2020 [J.6] Yingwei Zhang, Yiqiang Chen, Hanchao Yu, Zeping Lv, Xiaodong Yang, Chunyu Hu, **Tengxiang Zhang**. What Can "Drag & Drop" Tell? Detecting Mild Cognitive Impairment by Hand Motor Function Assessment under Dual-Task Paradigm. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies 145:102547.
  - [C.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Zeng, Yinshuai Zhang, Ke Sun, Yuntao Wang, and Yiqiang Chen. 2020. ThermalRing: Gesture and Tag Inputs Enabled by a Thermal Imaging Smart Ring. *In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1–13.
  - [C.2] Yuntao Wang, Zichao (Tyson) Chen, Hanchuan Li, Zhengyi Cao, Huiyi Luo, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Ke Ou, John Raiti, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. 2020. MoveVR: Enabling Multiform Force Feedback in Virtual Reality using Household Cleaning Robot. *In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20)*, 1–12.
  - [O.4] **Tengxiang Zhang** and Steve Hodges. New Opportunities for Sustainable Interaction using Backscatter Sensors. *Workshop on self-powered sustainable interfaces and interactions (SelfSustainableCHI 2020)*
- **2019** [J.5] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Jiayuan Gao, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Simin Li, Yuanchun Shi. Facilitating Temporal Synchronous Target Selection through User Behavior Modeling. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 2,4:159.
  - [J.4] Yuntao Wang, Jianyu Zhou, Hanchuan Li, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Minxuan Gao, Zhuolin Cheng, Chun Yu, Shwetak Patel, and Yuanchun Shi. FlexTouch: Enabling Large-Scale Interaction Sensing Beyond Touchscreens Using Flexible and Conductive Materials. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.*, 3,3:109.
  - [O.3] Jianfei Shen, **Tengxiang Zhang**, and Yiqiang Chen. Tap2Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Tapping. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '19*, *Pages 346-349*.

- **2018** [J.3] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Ruolin Wang, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu, Yiqin Lu, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. Tap-to-Pair: Associating Wireless Devices with Synchronous Tapping. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 2, 4: 201.
  - [O.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**. 2018. Toward Pervasive Interaction: Empowering and Enriching Interactions on Resource-constrained Devices. *Adjunct Proceedings of UbiComp/ISWC '18*, Pages 504-509.
  - [O.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2018. TOUCHPOWER: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *GetMobile: Mobile Comp. and Comm.* 22, 2: 27–31. (*Invited Highlights*)
- **2017** [J.2] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Xin Yi, Chun Yu, Yuntao Wang, Nicholas Becker, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. TouchPower: Interaction-based Power Transfer for Power-as-needed Devices. *Proc. ACM Interact. Mob. Wearable Ubiquitous Technol.* 1, 3: 121:1–121:20. (*Discussion Paper*)
  - [C.1] **Tengxiang Zhang**, Nicholas Becker, Yuntao Wang, Yuan Zhou, and Yuanchun Shi. 2017. BitID: Easily Add Battery-Free Wireless Sensors to Everyday Objects. *In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Smart Computing (SMARTCOMP)*, 1–8. (Best Paper Runner-up)
- **2013** [J.1] Huifeng Ma, Bengeng Cai, **Tengxiang Zhang**, Yan Yang, Weixiang Jiang, and Tiejun Cui. 2013. Three-Dimensional Gradient-Index Materials and Their Applications in Microwave Lens Antennas. *IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation* 61, 5: 2561–2569.

### **PATENTS**

- **2020** [P.9] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Input Method, System, and Apparatus: CN 202010413596.3 (*pending*)
  - [P.8] **Tengxiang Zhang,** Xin Zeng, Yiqiang Chen. A Smart Ring Based Gesture Recognition Method and System: CN 202010411317.X (*pending*)
  - [P.7] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. Apparatus and Method for Cognitive Load Analysis Based on Near-infrared Imaging of Subcutaneous Veins: CN 202010459503.0 (pending)
  - [P.6] Tengxiang Zhang, Jiayuan Gao, Yiqiang Chen. A Movement Symmetry Based Smart Prosthesis Control Method and System: CN 202010425034.0 (pending)
- **2018** [P.5] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. Smart Ring and its Wearing Method: CN 201810971684.8 (*pending*)
  - [P.4] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, **Tengxiang Zhang**. One type of Smart Ring: CN 201821371671.9
  - [P.3] Yuanchun Shi, Yinshuai Zhang, Tengxiang Zhang. Smart Ring: CN 201821371641.8
  - [P.2] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang and Chun Yu. Pairing method and wireless device for pairing using wireless signals. International Patent No. PCT/CN2018/094468.

[P.1] Yuanchun Shi, Tengxiang Zhang, Xin Yi, Yuntao Wang, Chun Yu. An association method and apparatus to pair devices based on wireless signals: CN 201810723952.4

### **GRANTS**

- **2020** [I.2] **Principle Investigator:** Resources Cross-modality Association and Matching Techniques (1.08 Million CNY), sub-project of Key Technologies for Modern Service Resource Management, National Key Research and Development Plan.
  - [I.1] **Co-investigator:** Hearing Aid Automatic Fitting Models (0.3 Million CNY), Key Technologies of Proactive Health and Aging Population, National Key Research and Development Plan.

### **HONORS AND AWARDS**

2019	Graduate with Honor (CS), Tsinghua University, China	
2018	Finalist, Global Innovation Competition'18	
2017	Best Paper Runner-up, SMARTCOMP'17	
2017	Discussion Paper, UbiComp'17	
2012	First Prize, International Mathematical Contest in Modeling	

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# 2019-present Assistant Research Scientist, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

- Conduct research on ultra-low-power sensors, wearable devices, and humancentered interconnections techniques
- Ubiquitous sensing hardware: Analog backscatter wireless touch sensing interface with μW power consumption (*on-going*)
- User-centered collaborative system: AR-facilitated digital resource manipulation (on-going)
- Pervasive interaction technique: Function association mechanism for gesture interfaces (*on-going*)

#### 2015-2016 RF Engineer/Product Manager, Tomoon Technology, Beijing, China

- Smartwatch and Bluetooth tracker antenna design
- Bluetooth tracker product definition, project management, field deployment

### 2013-2015 Product and Test Engineer, Silicon Labs, Austin, Texas, USA

- IoT MCU chips (e.g. Sub-GHz, ZigBee) RF calibration and test
- Test program (C/Perl) development, hardware design and layout
- Developed on-chip test program that saved over 30% test time for EM357

### **SERVICES**

Review CHI'20, IMWUT'20, UIST'20, MobileHCI'20, ISS'20, IUI'20,

TEI'20, EICS'19, TEI'21 WIP Program Committee

**Volunteer** ACM UBICOMP/ISWC 2018, Singapore;

The 4th UN World Urban Forum 2008, Nanjing, China

Academic Speaker GIX 2020 Access Computing Summer Program

**Mentor** GIX 2019 Winter Camp

# STUDENT SUPERVISION AND MENTORSHIP

**Xin Zeng** UCAS Ph.D (CS). Co-supervising with Prof. Yiqiang Chen

Xinyi YangBJTU Undergraduate (CS)Xinran ChenUESTC Undergraduate (CS)

Jiayuan GaoTsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Ph.D at UCAS (CS)\*Jiayin WangTsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Tsinghua (CS)\*Simin LiBeihang Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Georgia Tech (CS)\*Zi QianTsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at U of Toronto (CS)\*Hsuan-Wei FanTsinghua Undergraduate (CS); Now Master at Cornell Tech (CS)\*Hanwei WangTsinghua Undergraduate (Physics); Now Ph.D at UIUC (EE)

\* Alumni

### **SKILLS**

**Programming languages:** Python, C, C++, C#, Java, Matlab

**Prototyping**: Arduino, Processing, Altium, 3D printing

**Software:** Matlab, CST, Keras, Scikit-learn

**Hardware**: Signal generator, Vector network analyzer, Spectrum analyzer